<eml:eml xmlns:eml="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.1" xsi:schemaLocation="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0 https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0/eml.xsd" packageId="ess-dive-f9156555a3b4a8d-20241008T201459487" system="ess-dive"><dataset><title>Model code and data: biomass allocation adjustments induced by elevated CO2 and warming in a C3 brackish marsh, 2017-2022, Maryland</title><creator id="2285387124763159"><individualName><givenName>Nicholas</givenName><surName>Bruns</surName></individualName><organizationName>Virginia Institute of Marine Sciene</organizationName><electronicMailAddress>nebruns@vims.edu</electronicMailAddress><userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9518-2243</userId></creator><creator id="7662858121737361"><individualName><givenName>Genevieve</givenName><surName>Noyce</surName></individualName><organizationName>Smithsonian Environmental Research Center</organizationName><electronicMailAddress>noyceg@si.edu</electronicMailAddress><userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-0423-6478</userId></creator><creator id="2570922301536237"><individualName><givenName>Roy</givenName><surName>Rich</surName></individualName><organizationName>Smithsonian Environmental Research Center</organizationName><electronicMailAddress>richr@si.edu</electronicMailAddress><userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0461-7388</userId></creator><creator id="1785379262356393"><individualName><givenName>Patrick</givenName><surName>Megonigal</surName></individualName><organizationName>Smithsonian Environmental Research Center</organizationName><electronicMailAddress>megonigalp@si.edu</electronicMailAddress><userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2018-7883</userId></creator><associatedParty id="3266683853473404"><organizationName>U.S. DOE &#x3E; Office of Science &#x3E; Biological and Environmental Research (BER)</organizationName><userId directory="unknown">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/100006206</userId><role>fundingOrganization</role></associatedParty><pubDate>2024</pubDate><abstract><para>This dataset and R script accompany the published paper Bruns et al. (2024) in Geophysical Research Letters. The data are from the first six years of a field manipulation of whole-ecosystem warming and elevated CO2 experiment (Salt Marsh Accretion Response to Temperature eXperiment, or SMARTX) in the Smithsonian's Global Change Research Wetland (GCReW), a brackish, microtidal wetland site on a subestuary of the Chesapeake Bay. These data were generated to understand how warming and elevated CO2 interact to structure ecosystem-level responses to global change, particularly in terms of carbon sequestration. The dataset covers 2017-2022 and includes peak annual above ground biomass, annual belowground fine root productivity, and porewater NH4 for each experimental plot. The overall experiment is replicated in two locations on the marsh, a lower elevation zone dominated the C3 sedge S. Americanus and a higher elevation plot dominated by the C4 species. This paper and its data release is only for the C3 plot. Variable descriptions for data file is available in variable_descriptions.pdf. The R script Bruns_et_al_2024_GRL_make_figures.Rmd contains model code and other scripts used to generate all paper figures.</para></abstract><keywordSet><keyword>EARTH SCIENCE &#x3E; BIOSPHERE &#x3E; VEGETATION</keyword><keyword>EARTH SCIENCE &#x3E; BIOSPHERE &#x3E; ECOSYSTEMS</keyword><keyword>EARTH SCIENCE &#x3E; LAND SURFACE &#x3E; SOILS</keyword><keyword>EARTH SCIENCE &#x3E; BIOSPHERE &#x3E; ECOLOGICAL DYNAMICS</keyword><keywordThesaurus>CATEGORICAL:GCMD</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>Coastal wetland</keyword><keyword>Elevated CO2</keyword><keyword>warming</keyword><keyword>multi-factor global change experiment</keyword><keywordThesaurus>CATEGORICAL:NONE</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>EARTH SCIENCE &#x3E; BIOSPHERE &#x3E; ECOLOGICAL DYNAMICS &#x3E; ECOSYSTEM FUNCTIONS &#x3E; PRIMARY PRODUCTION</keyword><keyword>EARTH SCIENCE &#x3E; BIOSPHERE &#x3E; ECOSYSTEMS &#x3E; MARINE ECOSYSTEMS &#x3E; COASTAL &#x3E; SALT MARSH</keyword><keyword>EARTH SCIENCE &#x3E; BIOSPHERE &#x3E; ECOLOGICAL DYNAMICS &#x3E; ECOSYSTEM FUNCTIONS &#x3E; BIOMASS DYNAMICS</keyword><keyword>EARTH SCIENCE &#x3E; LAND SURFACE &#x3E; SOILS &#x3E; NITROGEN</keyword><keywordThesaurus>VARIABLE:GCMD</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><keywordSet><keyword>fine root productivity</keyword><keyword>belowground biomass</keyword><keyword>porewater nitrogen</keyword><keywordThesaurus>VARIABLE:NONE</keywordThesaurus></keywordSet><additionalInfo><section><title>Related References</title><para>Bruns, N. E., Noyce, G. L., Megonigal, J. P., Kirwan M.L, A test of functional balance theory for wetland biomass allocation in a global change experiment. Geophysical Research Letters. Accepted September 26, 2024.</para><para>Noyce, G. L., Kirwan, M. L., Rich, R. L., &#x26; Megonigal, J. P. (2019). Asynchronous nitrogen supply and demand produce nonlinear plant allocation responses to warming and elevated CO 2. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 116(43), 21623–21628. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1904990116</para></section></additionalInfo><intellectualRights><para>This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/.</para></intellectualRights><coverage><geographicCoverage><geographicDescription>This experiment occurred at the Global Change REsearch Wetland at the Smithsonian Environmental Research Center in  Edgewater, MD. The overall experiment is replicated in two locations on the marsh, a lower elevation zone dominated the C3 sedge S. Americanus and a higher elevation plot dominated by the C4 species. This paper and its data release is only for the C3 plot. 

38°53′ N, 76°33′ W

northwest
38.874041245867126, -76.55000438676342
southeast
38.87384801841697, -76.54968834484843</geographicDescription><boundingCoordinates><westBoundingCoordinate>-76.55000438676342</westBoundingCoordinate><eastBoundingCoordinate>-76.54968834484843</eastBoundingCoordinate><northBoundingCoordinate>38.874041245867126</northBoundingCoordinate><southBoundingCoordinate>38.87384801841697</southBoundingCoordinate></boundingCoordinates></geographicCoverage><temporalCoverage><rangeOfDates><beginDate><calendarDate>2017</calendarDate></beginDate><endDate><calendarDate>2022</calendarDate></endDate></rangeOfDates></temporalCoverage></coverage><contact id="1327895087823637"><individualName><givenName>Nicholas</givenName><surName>Bruns</surName></individualName><organizationName>Virginia Institute of Marine Science</organizationName><electronicMailAddress>nebruns@vims.edu</electronicMailAddress><userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-9518-2243</userId></contact><publisher id="9001097798643995"><organizationName>Coastal Wetland Carbon Cycling Processes in a Warmer Climate</organizationName></publisher><methods><methodStep><description><para>Complete methods are available in:</para><para>Noyce, G. L., Kirwan, M. L., Rich, R. L., &#x26; Megonigal, J. P. (2019). Asynchronous nitrogen supply and demand produce nonlinear plant allocation responses to warming and elevated CO 2. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 116(43), 21623–21628. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1904990116</para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para>Site description and experimental design</para><para>This work was conducted using the Salt Marsh Accretion Response to Temperature eXperiment (SMARTX)19 in the Smithsonian’s Global Change Research Wetland (GCReW), a brackish high marsh on the western shore of the Chesapeake Bay, U.S.A. (38°55’ N, 76°33’ W). The full experiment consists of 30 plots set up across six warming transects; each plot is 2 x 2 m in area and surrounded by a 0.2-m buffer to mitigate edge effects. Three transects are in a high-elevation area dominated by Spartina patens and Distichlis spicata, flooded on 10 to 20 % of high tides, and three are in a low-elevation area dominated by Schoenoplectus americanus, an herbaceous species that is known to respond rapidly to global change, and flooded on 30 to 60 % of high tides. The S. americanus site has an additional elevated CO2 treatment.</para><para>For this analysis we used the full subset of 12 plots from the S. americanus site that comprise a complete factorial design with two temperature levels (ambient and +5.1°C of warming) and two CO2 levels (ambient and +350 ppm). Each treatment combination is replicated three times.</para><para>In the warmed plots, aboveground plant-surface temperature is elevated with infrared heaters and soil temperature is elevated with vertical resistance cables. Temperature differentials are maintained by integrated microprocessor-based feedback control. Elevated CO2 plots are surrounded with 2-m-diameter open-top chambers and CO2 concentrations are independently controlled in each chamber. Warming was initiated in Jun 2016 and runs year-round. Elevated CO2 was initiated in Apr 2017 and is applied during daylight hours throughout the growing season. For this analysis, we used the first 6 years with both warming and eCO2 treatments.</para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para>Vegetation data</para><para>Root productivity was assessed using year-long root ingrowth cores, with three replicate cores per plot. Roots and rhizomes were hand-picked from each core, separated into functional groups, oven-dried at 60 °C, then weighed. Only fine root biomass was used for further analysis. The presence or absence of rhizomes is poorly sampled by the ingrowth cores, and thus their inclusion obscures the detection of treatment effects on belowground processes. Outlier data points, typically due to broken cores, were removed using Grubbs test (1.4 % of data), then the remaining replicate cores were averaged to give a per-plot value before statistical tests.</para><para>Stem productivity was calculated by allometry at peak biomass the first week of Aug each year. Within each 2 m x 2 m treatment plot we censused 30-cm x 30-cm permanent subplots (ambient CO2: n = 6; elevated CO2: n =5) for the number, height, and width of living stems. This data set reports biomass values, calculated from the census data using allometric equations, then subplots were averaged per plot.</para></description></methodStep><methodStep><description><para>Porewater Sampling and Analysis.</para><para>Porewater samples were collected in July of each year using stainless steel “sippers” permanently installed in each plot. Each sipper consisted of a length of stainless steel tubing, crimped and sealed at the end, with slits cut in the bottom 2 cm. The aboveground portion of each sipper was connected to Teflon tubing capped with a 2-way stopcock. Duplicate clusters of sippers were installed in each of the 30 plots at 10, 20, 40, 80, and 120 cm below the soil surface. Initial experiment years (2017-2018) also cover 50 and 100cm. Porewater sitting in the sippers was drawn up and discarded, after which 60 mL of porewater from each depth (30 mL from each sipper) was withdrawn and stored in syringes equipped with 3-way stopcocks. Within 3 h, samples were filtered through preleached syringe filters (0.45 μm) and frozen until further analysis. NH4 concentrations were measured using a Berthelot-salicylate colorimetric technique, modified to work in a 96-well microplate. Samples were run in triplicate and were all above the minimum detection limit of 0.05 ppm NH4. Nitrate concentrations at this site are &#x3C;0.05% of NH4 concentrations, so NH4 is assumed to represent all plant-available N.</para></description></methodStep></methods><project id="3c34c353-2626-4d56-b073-dcbdb19e01eb" scope="system" system="ess-dive"><title>Coastal Wetland Carbon Cycling Processes in a Warmer Climate</title><personnel id="5836465841445040"><individualName><givenName>Patrick</givenName><surName>Megonigal</surName></individualName><organizationName>Smithsonian Institution</organizationName><electronicMailAddress>megonigalp@si.edu</electronicMailAddress><role>principalInvestigator</role></personnel><funding><para>DOE:DE-SC0014413</para><para>DOE:DE-SC0019110</para><para>DOE:DE-SC0021112</para></funding></project><otherEntity id="ess-dive-05591ba83f04bc2-20241006T165049030"><entityName>SMARTX_data_2017_2022.csv</entityName><entityType>text/csv</entityType></otherEntity><otherEntity id="ess-dive-ee9e58b0aec6766-20241006T165033085"><entityName>Bruns_et_al_2024_GRL_make_figures.Rmd</entityName><entityType>application/octet-stream</entityType></otherEntity><otherEntity id="ess-dive-3eaf5e2a7f09e5b-20241008T201211356"><entityName>variable_descriptions.pdf</entityName><entityType>application/pdf</entityType></otherEntity></dataset></eml:eml>